Guide to the Jack Metcalf Papers 1973-2001
Western Washington University, Center for Pacific Northwest Studies
Jack Metcalf Papers
1973-2001
1981-2000
Center for Pacific Northwest Studies Goltz-Murray Building 808 25th St Bellingham, WA 98225-9123 Phone: 360 650 7534 Email: cpnws@wwu.edu
XOE_CPNWS0043metcalf
Metcalf, Jack.
28 linear ft.
The Jack Metcalf Papers document two decades of Metcalf’s political career as a Washington State Senator and as Representative for Washington State’s 2nd Congressional District. Collection materials comprise a small amount of records documenting Metcalf's activities during his final terms in the Washington State Legislature, and legislative issue files, correspondence, press files and awards from Metcalf's congressional offices in Washington D.C. and Everett, Washington.
Born in Marysville, Washington in 1927, Jack Metcalf served in the US military and as a boat skipper with the Fish and Wildlife Service during the 1940s. He graduated from Pacific Lutheran University with a BA and BEd. in 1951, and later pursued graduate studies in history and economics, earning an MA at the University of Washington in 1966. Metcalf worked as a high school math and history teacher in Everett, Washington for nearly thirty years.
Metcalf began his political career in state government, serving as a Republican member of the Washington State House of Representatives (1961-1964) and later the Washington State Senate (1967-1975 and 1981-1993), where he chaired the Senate Environmental and Natural Resources Committee between 1988 and 1992. In 1994, as the Republican Party gained control of the U.S. House of Representatives, Metcalf was elected representative for Washington State's 2nd Congressional District.
Often described as a political conservative, Metcalf was concerned with a wide range of legislative issues. He served as a member of the House Banking, Transportation and Infrastructure, and Science Committees, and on subcommittees for Ground Transportation, Aviation, Financial Institutions and International Monetary Policy. As a politician and legislator, Metcalf focused much of his attention on regionally significant issues including Puget Sound transportation development, natural resource and fisheries management, and environmental protection. In 1997, Metcalf and U.S. Senator Patty Murray (D-Washington) established the Northwest Straits Advisory Commission, a bipartisan body intended to conserve marine life in Northwest Washington. Metcalf also led an unsuccessful challenge to the resumption of whaling by the Makah Indian Tribe in Neah Bay, Washington.
A long-time advocate for the US military and military personnel, Metcalf pursued investigations into the origins of Gulf War Illnesses, sought funding to assist military families in Washington State, and in 1997 introduced the Robert Stodola Veterans Assistance Act to increase funding for homeless veterans’ programs. As chair of the Republican Housing Opportunity Caucus, Metcalf supported the Low Income Housing Tax credit program to encourage development of affordable homes.
An outspoken supporter of congressional term limits, Metcalf retired from the House of Representatives in 2000 after serving three terms. He lived in Langley on Whidbey Island, Washington until his death in March of 2007.
The Jack Metcalf Papers document two decades of Metcalf’s political career as a Washington State Senator and United States Congressman. Collection materials span the period 1973-2001, with the bulk of materials dated 1981-2000. Pre-congressional records comprise approximately one linear foot of material generated during Metcalf’s final years as a Senator in the Washington State Legislature (1981-1993). Alphabetically-arranged Legislative Issue files document Metcalf’s long-standing opposition to the U.S. Federal Reserve, and his role as head of the Senate Environmental and Natural Resources Committee between 1988-1992. These files include correspondence, reports, surveys and articles reflecting communication and conflict between the Washington State Department of Wildlife and Fisheries, Washington Wildlife Commission, Tribes and other interest groups over hunting rights and restrictions. Pre-congressional materials also contain a small number of awards and certificates of appreciation Metcalf received for his legislative work. With the exception of one “Outstanding Senator” award from 1973, the collection does not document Metcalf’s activities in the Washington State Legislature prior to 1981.
Congressional Records document Jack Metcalf’s role and interests as representative for Washington State’s 2nd Congressional District between 1994 and 2000. The majority of Congressional records were generated at Metcalf’s offices in Washington D.C., with a smaller amount of material (approximately three linear feet) from his District Office in Everett, Washington.
D.C. Office materials include a significant number of “Legislative Issue” files, grouped together according to subject (A-Z). These files include variously correspondence, memos, notes, statements, articles, and draft legislation pertaining to twenty-four broad areas of legislative concern. Many of Metcalf’s political activities focused on issues of immediate significance to the Pacific Northwest and his constituents in Washington State. Legislative Issue files document his roles in securing appropriations for transportation projects in the Puget Sound region, and seeking relief for fishers affected adversely by the downturn in the fishing industry at the end of the twentieth century. The collection documents many of the ongoing conflicts between environmental and commercial interests over protection, use and development of local resources, including National Park and National Forest Land, fisheries, waterways, and industrial clean-up sites. Whale and Marine Mammal files detail Metcalf’s active opposition to whaling by the Makah Indian Tribe in Neah Bay, Washington, while Water and Shipping files record his bipartisan efforts to enact the Northwest Straits Marine Conservation Initiative (1998). The collection contains press clippings, correspondence, statements, hearings transcripts and reports documenting the aftermath of the June 10, 1999 gas pipeline explosion at Whatcom Creek in Bellingham, Washington, and subsequent attempts by legislators and community organizations to enact pipeline safety legislation.
Legislative issue files pertaining to Aviation, Defense and US Military, Education, and Housing reflect Metcalf’s active support for local military contract bids, concern with the interests of local military families, his investigations into Gulf War Syndrome, and his active support for homeless veterans programs. Materials related to Defense and the Executive Branch record Metcalf’s opposition to Clinton’s alleged expansion and misuse of executive authority, notably through his troop deployments in Kosovo. Legislative Issue files also document Metcalf’s legislative involvement in areas of Banking and Investment, Agricultural, Health and Immigration policy, Energy Provision, Science and Telecommunications, Tribal Issues and International Trade and Foreign Affairs.
Metcalf’s D.C. Office Files include correspondence files dated 1995-2000. The majority of letters are outgoing from Metcalf (often in coalition with other legislators) to correspondents including the President, White House officials, the Speaker of the House, leaders of House Committees, and key figures in the private and non-government sector. Press Files comprise photographs, press statements and releases pertaining to Metcalf’s legislative concerns, and partial documentation of Metcalf’s congressional voting record. D.C. Office files also include a small number of awards and certificates Metcalf earned for his legislative work.
Metcalf’s congressional papers also contain a smaller amount of material (approximately three linear feet) generated at Metcalf’s District Office in Everett, Washington. The bulk of District Office records are subject-based Legislative Issue files. Articles, hearing transcripts and reports document Metcalf’s investigation into links between military vaccines and Gulf War Illnesses among Persian Gulf veterans, and include a copy of his 2000 report entitled Potential Role of Squalene in Gulf War Illnesses, submitted to the House Subcommittee on National Security, Veterans Affairs, and International Relations. The subseries also contains materials regarding military issues and local military bases, Lummi Indian Nation requests for federal assistance, Swinomish leaseholds and water rights, the local fishing industry and regional transportation and environmental projects. District office files include a further number of awards and certificates presented to Metcalf.
The Jack Metcalf Papers are organized in accordance with the following series and subseries arrangement:
Series I. Pre-Congressional Career 1973-1992 (bulk 1981-1992)
Series II. Congressional Career 1984-2001 (bulk 1995-2000)
Subseries 1. Washington D.C. Office Files, 1984-2001
Subseries 2. District Office Files, 1995-2000
The collection is open to the public.
S. Lewis Moore, head of Jack Metcalf’s district office in Everett, Washington, transferred the collection to the Center for Pacific Northwest Studies in 2001.
The Washington State Archives in Olympia houses a small number of additional records documenting Metcalf’s career in the Washington State Senate.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Metcalf, Jack, 1927- --Archives.
Washington (State). -- Legislature. -- Senate.; United States. --Congress.; Olympic Pipeline Company -- Explosion, 1999.; Washington (State). -- Dept. of Fish and Wildlife.
United States -- Politics and government -- 20th century -- History -- Sources.; Washington (State) -- Politics and government -- History -- Sources.; United States -- Armed Forces.
Politicians -- Washington (State) -- History -- Sources.; Politicians -- United States -- History -- Sources.; Law and legislation -- United States -- History -- Sources.; Aircraft industry -- United States -- History -- Sources.; Agricultural industries -- Law and legislation -- United States -- History -- Sources.; Banks and banking -- Law and legislation -- United States -- History -- Sources.; Education -- Law and legislation -- United States -- History -- Sources.; Schools -- Washington (State) -- Funding -- History -- Sources.; Medical Care -- Law and legislation -- United States -- History -- Sources.; Homeless veterans -- Law and legislation -- United States -- History -- Sources.; Low-income housing -- Law and legislation -- United States -- History -- Sources.; Energy policy -- Washington (State) -- History -- Sources.; Environmental policy -- United States -- History -- Sources.; Environmental policy -- Washington -- History -- Sources.; Hazardous waste sites -- United States -- History -- Sources.; Hazardous waste sites -- Washington (State) -- History -- Sources.; Wildlife conservation -- Washington (State) -- History -- Sources.; Wildlife conservation -- Northwest, Pacific -- History -- Sources.; Forest management -- Northwest, Pacific -- History -- Sources.; Salmon -- Conservation -- United States -- History -- Sources.; Salmon -- Conservation -- Northwest, Pacific -- History -- Sources.; Salmon fisheries -- Law and legislation -- Pacific Area -- History -- Sources.; Salmon fisheries -- Washington (State) -- History -- Sources.; Gasoline pipelines -- Accidents -- Investigation -- Washington(State) -- Whatcom Creek Region -- History -- Sources.; Emigration and immigration law -- United States -- History -- Sources.; International relations -- United States -- History -- Sources.; Indians of North America -- Washington (State) -- Fishing -- History -- Sources.; Indians of North America -- Washington (State) -- Hunting -- History -- Sources.; Indians of North America -- Legal status, laws, etc -- History -- Sources.; Lummi Indians -- History -- Sources.; Makah Indians -- Hunting -- Environmental aspects -- Washington (State) -- History -- Sources.; Whaling -- Washington (State) -- Neah Bay -- History -- Sources.; Telecommunication policy -- United States -- History -- Sources.; Water resources development -- Law and legislation -- United States -- History -- Sources.; Executive power -- United States -- History -- Sources.; Persian Gulf syndrome -- United States -- History -- Sources.; Transportation -- Washington (State) -- Planning -- History -- Sources.; Transportation -- Washington (State) -- Appropriations and expenditures -- History -- Sources.
Washington (State); Agriculture; Environmental conditions; Fisheries and wildlife; Forestry and Forestry products; Government and politics; International Relations; Logging; Medicine and health; Military; Native Americans; Public utilities; Science; Transportation
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- Pre-Congressional Records, 1973-1992; 1981-1992; Series I
  Pre-congressional records document Metcalf’s activities and concerns as a member of the Washington State Senate between 1981 and 1993, including his role as head of the Senate Environmental and Natural Resources Committee. The bulk of materials pertain to Metcalf’s dealings with the Washington State Department of Wildlife and Fisheries, and the Washington Wildlife Commission regarding hunting rights and restrictions. The series also documents Metcalf’s active opposition to the United States Federal Reserve.
  - Legislative Issues (A-Z)
    - Campaign Materials - 1992 Washington State Governor, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Campaign Materials - Congressional Campaign, 1992 (Box-folder 1/2)
    - Constituency newsletters and reports
      - Constituency newsletters In Touch: Legislative News and Comments, 1986-1992 (Box-folder 1/3)
      - Metcalf reports, 1982-1991 (Box-folder 1/4)
    - Federal Reserve - Correspondence to Legislators and constituents, 1982-1986 (Box-folder 1/5)
    - Federal Reserve Update Newsletters, 1983-1989 (Box-folder 1/6)
    - Federal Reserve - Newspaper articles, 1981-1982 (Box-folder 1/7)
    - Federal Reserve - Papers and publications
      - Kettering, Lynne. A Harvest of Violence. Olympia, Washington: An Honest Money for America Publication, 1987. (Box-folder 1/8)
      - Metcalf, Jack United States Economic Policies and the Federal Reserve System., 1982 October; revised 1985 March. (Box-folder 1/9)
      - Metcalf, Jack. The 200 Year Debate: Who Shall Issue The Nation’s Money? Olympia, Washington: An Honest Money for American Publication, 1986. (Box-folder 1/10)
      - Metcalf, Jack (compiler). Who Should Issue The Nation’s Money? Relevant Quotes on the Money Issue., Undated. (Box-folder 1/11)
      - Popp, Edward. The U.S. Government Can Be Paid Off! Olympia, Washington: An Honest Money For America Publication, 1986. (Box-folder 1/12)
      - Popp, Edward. There is no need for the US Government to incur interest-bearing debts. Port Washington, Wisconsin: Wisconsin Education Fund, 1990 (Box-folder 1/13)
      - Referendum 41, 1987 (Box-folder 1/14)
    - Washington State Department of Fisheries
      - Correspondence, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 1/15)
      - Transcripts of hearing re: Senate Bill 5050, 1987 (Box-folder 1/16)
      - Injury to Marine Mammals, circa 1989 (Box-folder 1/17)
    - Washington State Department of Wildlife
      - Curt Smitch appointment, 1987-1991 (Box-folder 1/18 - 1/19)
      - Correspondence, 1987-1992 (Box-folder 1/20)
      - Newspaper Clippings, circa 1988-1992 (Box-folder 1/21)
      - Employee Surveys, 1991 December (Box-folder 1/22 - 1/23)
      - Employee Anonymous letters, circa 1989 (Box-folder 1/24)
      - Overtime / Holland Case, 1991 (Box-folder 1/25)
      - Tribal Hunting and Nooksack Elk Herd, 1988-1992 (Box-folder 1/26)
      - Washington State Tribal Hunting Agreements, 1987-1989 (Box-folder 1/27)
    - Washington Wildlife Commission
      - Correspondence, 1988-1990 (Box-folder 1/28)
      - License Fee Marketing Analysis Report, 1989 (Box-folder 1/29)
  - Awards and Certificates
    - Outstanding Senator (Young Americans for Freedom), 1973 (Box-folder 1/30)
    - Certificates of Appreciation, 1987-1989 (Box-folder 1/31)
    - Institutional Industries (Board of Directors) certificate, 1981 (Oversize-folder 1)
    - Seattle Times Brian Bassett Cartoon, 1987 (Oversize-folder 1)
- Congressional Career, 1984-2001; 1995-2000; Series II
  - Washington D.C. Office files, 1984-2001; (bulk 1995-2000); Subseries 1
    - Legislative Issues, 1984-2001
      - Agriculture and Food Industry, 1996-2000
        Records reflect industry responses to legislation including federal milk pricing, food contamination and labeling, and alien worker programs. In 1999, Metcalf co-sponsored the Genetically Engineered Right To Know Act (H.R. 3377) with Representative Dennis Kucinich (D-Ohio) and other members of Congress.
        - Agricultural Research, 1997-1998 (Box-folder 2/1)
        - Agricultural Trade (International), 1998-1999 (Box-folder 2/2)
        - Agricultural Workers - H-2A Guest Worker Program, 2000 (Box-folder 2/3)
        - Canadian Cattle Imports, 1999 (Box-folder 2/4)
        - Conservation Reserve Program, 1996 (Box-folder 2/5)
        - Dairy Producers and Federal Milk Pricing System (H.R. 1402), 1999 (Box-folder 2/6)
        - Farm Bureau Crisis Relief, 1999 (Box-folder 2/7)
        - Farmland Preservation, 1997-1998 (Box-folder 2/8)
        - Food Quality Protection Act, 1996 (Box-folder 2/9)
        - Food Quality Protection Act, 1998-1999 (Box-folder 2/10)
        - Genetically Engineered Foods, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 2/11)
        - Grazing - Forage Improvement Act (H.R. 2493), 1997 (Box-folder 2/12)
        - Legislation re: Farming and Agricultural Workers, 1996-1998 (Box-folder 2/13)
        - Meat Labeling, 1999 (Box-folder 2/14)
        - Methyl Bromide, 1998 (Box-folder 2/15)
        - Precision Agriculture, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 2/16)
        - Quincy Fertilizer Issue, 1997 (Box-folder 2/17)
        - Sheep and Lambs – Washington Production and Income, 1999 (Box-folder 2/18)
        - Total Maximum Daily Load Rule (Clean Water Act), 2000 (Box-folder 2/19)
        - United States-Russia Maritime Boundary Agreement, 1997 (Box-folder 2/20)
        - USDA- Food Aid to Russia, 1998 (Box-folder 2/21)
        - USDA Food Safety & Inspection Service – Labeling Review for meat, poultry & egg products (“Schenk Packing Co.”), 1998 (Box-folder 2/22)
        - Washington State University- Mount Vernon Research Station Land Security Project, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 2/23)
      - Appropriations, circa 1997-2000
        Copies of budget proposals, resolutions, notes, correspondence and reports pertaining to budget appropriations and related issues.
        - FY 1998 - Agricultural Appropriations, circa 1997 (Box-folder 2/24)
        - FY 1998 - Energy and Water Appropriations, circa 1997 (Box-folder 2/25)
        - FY 1998 - Interior Appropriations, circa 1997 (Box-folder 2/26)
        - FY 1998 - State Hatcheries, circa 1997 (Box-folder 2/27)
        - FY 1999 – Agricultural Appropriations, circa 1998 (Box-folder 2/28)
        - FY 1999 - Communications Satellite Competition and Privatization (H.R. 1872), circa 1998 (Box-folder 2/29)
        - FY 1999 – Departments of Commerce, Justice and State, circa 1998 (Box-folder 2/30)
        - FY 1999 - Energy and Water Appropriations, 1998 (Box-folder 2/31)
        - FY 1999 - Interior Appropriations, 1998 (Box-folder 2/32)
        - FY 1999 - 1999 Omnibus Appropriations, 1998 (Box-folder 2/33)
        - FY 1999 - Treasury/Postal Appropriations, 1998 (Box-folder 2/34)
        - FY 1999 - Veterans Affairs and Housing and Urban Development Appropriations (Kyoto Protocol), 1998 (Box-folder 2/35)
        - FY 2000 - Agricultural Appropriations, circa 1999 (Box-folder 3/1)
        - FY 2000 – Budget Resolution, circa 1999 (Box-folder 3/2)
        - FY 2000 – Committee for a Resposible Federal Budget, circa 1999 (Box-folder 3/3)
        - FY 2000 - Emergency Supplemental Appropriations (Defense), circa 1999 (Box-folder 3/4)
        - FY 2000 - Energy and Water Appropriations, circa 1999 (Box-folder 3/5)
        - FY 2000 - Interior Appropriations, circa 1999 (Box-folder 3/6)
        - FY 2000 - Veterans Affairs and Housing and Urban Development Appropriations, circa 1999 (Box-folder 3/7)
      - Aviation Files, 1995-2000
        Aviation files reflect Metcalf’s interests as member of the House Aviation Subcommittee. Researchers should note that Defense and US Military files contain additional information regarding Boeing and McDonnell Douglas bids and contracts.
        - Aerospace Industries, 1997; 2000 (Box-folder 3/8)
        - Air-21 (Aviation trust), undated (Box-folder 3/9)
        - Air-21 Aviation Investment and Reform Act, 1999 (Box-folder 3/10)
        - Airbus Superjumbo, undated (Box-folder 3/11)
        - Aircraft, Stage 2 (FAA Reauthorization), 1999 (Box-folder 3/12)
        - Aircraft Owners and Pilots Association, 1998-1999 (Box-folder 3/13)
        - Airline Passenger Bill of Rights (H.R. 700), 1999 (Box-folder 3/14)
        - Airport Privatization, 1999 (Box-folder 3/15)
        - Alaska Airlines – Crew/Passenger Illness, 1999 (Box-folder 3/16)
        - Arlington Airport, 1995-1997 (Box-folder 3/17)
        - Aviation Subcommittee Hearings re: airline funding and safety, 1999 (Box-folder 3/18)
        - B-2 Bomber program, 1995 (Box-folder 3/19)
        - B-2 GATS/GAM 16-Drop: October 1996 - General Hawley Comments (Video cassette), 1997 (Box-folder 3/20)
        - Boeing – Aircraft Exports, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 3/21)
        - Boeing – Annual Reports, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 3/22)
        - Boeing - Defense and Space Group / International Trade Briefing, 1995 (Box-folder 3/23)
        - Boeing – IL 96TM Aircraft, 1996 (Box-folder 3/24)
        - Boeing – Joint Strike Fighter, undated (Box-folder 3/25)
        - Boeing – V-22 Osprey, undated (Box-folder 3/26)
        - C-17 Background Information File, circa 1996 (Box-folder 3/27)
        - C-17 Fact Sheet and Information, circa 1995 (Box-folder 3/28)
        - C-17 Program, circa 1996 (Box-folder 3/29)
        - Federal Aviation Authority “Age 60 Rule” for pilots, 1999 (Box-folder 3/30)
        - Federal Aviation Authority Management - Professional Airways Systems Specialists Report, 1999 (Box-folder 3/31)
        - Foreign Repair Station restrictions (H.R. 145), 1997 (Box-folder 3/32)
        - Hushkit regulation – European Union strategy, 1999 (Box-folder 3/33)
        - Industry Customer Service Plans, 1999 (Box-folder 3/34)
        - National Air Transportation Association – Aircraft Repair Stations, 1999 (Box-folder 3/35)
        - On-time Flight Performance Reporting, 1999 (Box-folder 3/36)
        - Port of Seattle, circa 2000 (Box-folder 3/37)
        - Prowler Day, 1999 (Box-folder 3/38)
        - Prowler (EA-6B) funding, 1999 (Box-folder 3/39)
        - Reagan National Airport, 1999 (Box-folder 3/40)
        - San Juan Islands - Canadian Airspace Proposal, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 3/41)
        - SEA-TAC Airport – 3rd Runway Project, 1995-1997 (Box-folder 4/1 - 4/2)
        - Transportation Appropriations Bill (H.R. 2084), 1999 (Box-folder 4/3)
        - Transportation Equity Act for the 21st Century, undated. (Box-folder 4/4)
        - US – China Air Service, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 4/5)
        - US – China Aviation Agreement (Northwest Airlines), 1999 (Box-folder 4/6)
      - Banking and Investment, 1990-2000; (bulk 1997-2000)
        A member of the House Banking Committee, Metcalf supported and introduced legislation that would enable businesses to earn interest on demand deposit accounts.